I think it's safe to say
أعتقد أنه لا ضير في قول،
that all humans will be intimate with death
أن "كل البشر سوف يألفون فكرة الموت"
at least once in their lives.
على الأقل مرة واحدة في حياتهم !
But what if that intimacy began
و لكن، ماذا لو بدأت تلك الألفة بالتنامي
long before you faced your own transition
قبل أن يحين موعد الإنتقال الى العالم الاخر بفترة طويلة
from life into death?
من الحياة الى الموت؟
What would life be like
كيف ستكون الحياة تحت هذا النهج؟
if the dead literally lived alongside you?
إذا عاش الميت بجانبك و بكل ما تعنيه الكلمة
In my husband's homeland
.. في موطن زوجي
in the highlands of Sulawesi island
عند أعالي جزيرة سولاوسي
in eastern Indonesia,
في شرقي اندونيسيا
there is a community of people that experience death
هنالك مجتمع يعيش تجربة الموت
not as a singular event
ليس كتجربة فردية..
but as a gradual social process.
و إنما في إطار مجموعة من الأفراد
In Tana Toraja,
في تانا توراجا
the most important social moments in people's lives,
اللحظات الأكثر أهمية في جانب التواصل بين أولئك الناس
the focal points of social and cultural interaction
نقاط التركيز في التفاعل الاجتماعي و الثقافي
are not weddings or births or even family dinners,
ليس في الأعراس أو أعياد الميلاد حتى إلتفاف العائلة حول مائدة الطعام
but funerals.
و إنما المآتم
So these funerals are characterized
إذاً فهذه المآتم قد مُيزّت
by elaborate rituals
بطقوس ذات تفاصيل دقيقة
that tie people in a system of reciprocal debt
و كفيلة بإبقاء الناس في موالاة متبادلة بين بعضهم البعض
based on the amount of animals --
وهي مبنية على حصيلة الحيوانات
pigs, chickens and, most importantly, water buffalo --
خنازير و دجاج و الأهم بين هذه الحيوانات (جاموس الماء)
that are sacrificed and distributed
التي سوف تقدم كقرابين، و من ثَم ستفرّق بين الناس
in the name of the deceased.
على روح الفقيد (المتوفى)
So this cultural complex surrounding death,
إذاً فهذه الثقافة المعقدة تحيط بالموت
the ritual enactment of the end of life,
أساسيات طقوس نهاية الحياة
has made death the most visible
قد جعلت من مفهوم الموت مفهومًا طاغيًا على هذه الثقافة
and remarkable aspect of Toraja's landscape.
و علامة بارزة لطبيعة التوراجا
Lasting anywhere from a few days
تنتشر و بإستمرار لأيام قليلة
to a few weeks,
أو لأسابيع،
funeral ceremonies are a raucous affair,
تكون إحتفالات المأتم صاخبة
where commemorating someone who's died
حيث يحيون فيها ذكرى الميت
is not so much a private sadness
تشبه المناسبات الحزينة الخاصة
but more of a publicly shared transition.
وإنما هي أقرب لمشاركة إنتقالية العامة
And it's a transition that's just as much
وأيضًا، هي فترة انتقالية تكون أقرب الى
about the identity of the living
تجسيد مفهوم الحياة
as it is about remembrance of the dead.
بينما هي في الأصل إحياء لذكرى أحدهم
So every year, thousands of visitors
ففي كل عام، الآلاف من الزوار
come to Tana Toraja to see, as it were,
يأتون الى تانا توراجا ليشهدوا
this culture of death,
هذه الإحتفالات الجنائزية،
and for many people these grandiose ceremonies
و يعتبرها الكثير من الناس شعائرٌ فخمة
and the length of the ceremonies
أما فترة الإحتفالات
are somehow incommensurable
فهي نوعا ما غير متناسبة
with the way that we face our own mortality in the West.
مع الطريقة التي نواجه بها الوفاة في الغرب
So even as we share death as a universal experience,
حتى و إن كنا نتشارك الموت كتجربة عالمية،
it's not experienced the same way the world over.
فنحن لا نختبرها بنفس الطريقة مع باقي العالم
And as an anthropologist,
و بإعتباري عالمة أنتروبولوجيا،
I see these differences in experience
أرى هذه الإختلافات في التجربة
being rooted in the cultural and social world
تتجذر في العالمين الثقاقي و الإجتماعي
through which we define the phenomena around us.
الذي من خلالهم نحدد الظواهر التي تحيط بنا.
So where we see an unquestionable reality,
و بالتالي حيث أننا نرى الموت واقعا لا شك فيه،
death as an irrefutable biological condition,
كحالة بيولوجية لا يمكن دحضها،
Torajans see the expired corporeal form
التوراجيون ( نسبة إلى توراجا ) يرون الشكل الجسدي المنتهي الصلاحية
as part of a larger social genesis.
كجزء من نشأة إجتماعية أوسع.
So again, the physical cessation of life
لذلك مجددا، التوقف الجسدي للحياة
is not the same as death.
ليس هو نفسه كما الموت.
In fact, a member of society is only truly dead
في الواقع، العضو في المجتمع يكون ميتا حقا
when the extended family can agree upon
فقط عندما تتفق الأسرة الممتدة على ذلك
and marshal the resources necessary
وتحشد الموارد اللازمة
to hold a funeral ceremony
لإقامة مراسم التشييع
that is considered appropriate in terms of resources
التي تعتبر مناسبة من حيث الموارد
for the status of the deceased.
لمكانة المتوفى.
And this ceremony has to take place
وهذه المراسم يجب أن تقام
in front of the eyes of the whole community
أمام أعين المجتمع كله
with everyone's participation.
و بمشاركة الجميع.
So after a person's physical death,
و هكذا بعد وفاة الشخص جسديا،
their body is placed in a special room
يتم وضع جسده في غرفة خاصة
in the traditional residence, which is called the tongkonan.
في الإقامة التقليدية، التي تسمى تونجكونان.
And the tongkonan is symbolic
و التونجكونان هو رمزي
not only of the family's identity
ليس فقط لهوية العائلة
but also of the human life cycle from birth to death.
بل أيضا لدورة حياة الإنسان من المهد إلى اللحد.
So essentially, the shape of the building
لذلك أساسا، شكل المبنى
that you're born into is the shape
الذي ولدت فيه هو شكل
of the structure which carries you
الهيكل الذي يحملك
to your ancestral resting place.
لمثوى أجدادك.
Until the funeral ceremony,
إلى أن تقام مراسم الجنازة،
which can be held years after a person's physical death,
والتي يمكن أن تعقد سنوات بعد الوفاة الجسدية للشخص،
the deceased is referred to as "to makala," a sick person,
يشار للمتوفى بإسم &amp;quot;تو ماكالا&amp;quot; شخص مريض،
or "to mama," a person who is asleep,
أو &amp;quot;تو ماما&amp;quot; شخص نائم،
and they continue to be a member of the household.
و يبقى عضوا في الأسرة.
They are symbolically fed and cared for,
يتم إطعامهم رمزيا ورعايتهم،
and the family at this time
والأسرة في هذا الوقت
will begin a number of ritual injunctions,
ستبدأ عددا من الطقوس الإحترازية،
which communicates to the wider community around them
التي تبلغ إلى المجتمع الأوسع من حولهم
that one of their members is undergoing the transition
أن واحدا من أعضائها يخضع للتحول
from this life into the afterlife
من هذه الحياة إلى الآخرة
known as Puya.
المعروفة بإسم پويا.
So I know what some of you must be thinking right now.
أنا أعرف في ماذا سيفكر بعض منكم في الوقت الحالي.
Is she really saying that these people live
هل هي حقا تقول إن هؤلاء الناس يعيشون
with the bodies of their dead relatives?
مع جثث أقاربهم الأموات؟
And that's exactly what I'm saying.
وهذا هو بالضبط ما أقوله.
But instead of giving in to the sort of visceral reaction
ولكن بدلا من الاستسلام لهذا النوع من رد الفعل الغريزي
we have to this idea of proximity to bodies,
هذه الفكرة عن القرب من الجثث،
proximity to death,
القرب من الموت،
or how this notion just does not fit
أو كيف أن هذا المفهوم لا يتناسب
into our very biological or medical
مع النوع البيولوجي و الطبي
sort of definition of death,
من تعريف الموت،
I like to think about what the Torajan way
أحب أن أفكر حول طريقة التوراجيين
of viewing death encompasses of the human experience
في رؤية الموت و هي تشمل التجربة الإنسانية
that the medical definition leaves out.
التي يتركها التعريف الطبي جانبا.
I think that Torajans socially recognize
أعتقد أن التوراجيين يعترفون إجتماعيا
and culturally express
ويعربون ثقافيا عن
what many of us feel to be true
ما يشعر به العديد منا على أنه صحيح
despite the widespread acceptance
على الرغم من القبول الواسع النطاق
of the biomedical definition of death,
للتعريف الطبي الحيوي للموت،
and that is that our relationships with other humans,
وأن علاقاتنا مع البشر،
their impact on our social reality,
و تأثيرهم على الواقع الاجتماعي لدينا،
doesn't cease with the termination
لايتوقف مع إنتهاء
of the physical processes of the body,
العمليات الفيزيائية في الجسم،
that there's a period of transition
أن هناك فترة انتقالية
as the relationship between the living and the dead
بينما العلاقة بين الأحياء والأموات
is transformed but not ended.
تتحول لكن لم تنته.
So Torajans express this idea of this enduring relationship
لذلك فإن التوراجيون يعبرون عن فكرة هذه علاقة دائمة
by lavishing love and attention
بواسطة السخاء في الحب والإهتمام
on the most visible symbol of that relationship,
تجاه الرمز الأكثر وضوحا من تلك العلاقة،
the human body.
جسم الإنسان.
So my husband has fond memories
زوجي لديه ذكريات جميلة
of talking to and playing with
في التحدث إلى واللعب مع
and generally being around his deceased grandfather,
و عموما التواجد حول جده المتوفى،
and for him there is nothing unnatural about this.
وبالنسبة له ليس هناك شيء غير طبيعي حول هذا الموضوع.
This is a natural part of the process
هذا جزء طبيعي من عملية
as the family comes to terms with the transition
حيث تتوصل الأسرة إلى تفاهم مع التحول
in their relationship to the deceased,
في علاقتها مع المتوفى،
and this is the transition from relating to the deceased
وهذا هو الإنتقال من العلاقة مع الميت
as a person who's living
بإعتباره الشخص الذي يعيش
to relating to the deceased
إلى علاقة معه
as a person who's an ancestor.
بأنه شخص من السلف.
And here you can see these wooden effigies
وهنا يمكنك أن ترى هذه الدمى الخشبية
of the ancestors,
للأسلاف،
so these are people who have already been buried,
إذن هؤلاء هم ناس تم من قبل دفنهم،
already had a funeral ceremony.
و حصلوا على مراسم التشييع.
These are called tau tau.
هؤلاء يسمون &amp;quot;تاو تاو&amp;quot;.
So the funeral ceremony itself
وبالتالي فإن مراسم الدفن نفسها
embodies this relational perspective on death.
تجسد هذا المنظور العلائقي في الموت.
It ritualizes the impact of death on families
فإنها تعطي طابعا شعائريا لأثر الموت على الأسر
and communities.
والمجتمعات المحلية.
And it's also a moment of self-awareness.
وإنها أيضا لحظة من الوعي الذاتي.
It's a moment when people think about who they are,
إنها لحظة عندما يفكر الناس في حقيقتهم،
their place in society,
مكانهم في المجتمع،
and their role in the life cycle
ودورهم في دورة الحياة
in accordance with Torajan cosmology.
وفقا لعلم الكونيات الطوراجي.
There's a saying in Toraja
هناك قول مأثور في توراجا
that all people will become grandparents,
أن جميع الناس سوف يصبحون أجدادا،
and what this means is that after death,
وما يعنيه هذا هو أنه بعد الموت،
we all become part of the ancestral line
أننا جميعا نصبح جزءا من الخط السلفي
that anchors us between the past and the present
الذي يربطنا بين الماضي والحاضر
and will define who our loved ones are into the future.
وسيحدد ماذا سيصبح أحبائنا في المستقبل.
So essentially, we all become grandparents
لذلك أساسا، نحن جميعا نصبح أجدادا
to the generations of human children
لأجيال من الأبناء
that come after us.
التي يأتون بعدنا.
And this metaphor of membership
وهذا التشبيه للعضوية
in the greater human family
في أكبر أسرة بشرية
is the way that children also describe
هي الطريقة التي يصفها الأبناء أيضا
the money that they invest
الأموال التي يستثمرونها
in these sacrificial buffaloes
في هذه الجواميس التي تعتبر قربانا
that are thought to carry people's soul
و التي يعتقد أن تحمل روح الناس
from here to the afterlife,
من هنا إلى الآخرة،
and children will explain
وسوف يشرح الأبناء
that they will invest the money in this
أنهم سوف يستثمرون الأموال في هذا
because they want to repay their parents
لأنهم يريدون أن يسددوا لأبائهم
the debt for all of the years their parents spent
الدين الذي صرفه والديهم طوال سنوات
investing and caring for them.
في الإستثمار فيهم ورعايتهم.
But the sacrifice of buffalo
ولكن التضحية بالجاموس
and the ritual display of wealth
وطقوس عرض الثروة
also exhibits the status of the deceased,
أيضا تعرض وضع المتوفى،
and, by extension, the deceased's family.
وإستطرادا، أسرة المتوفى.
So at funerals, relationships are reconfirmed
حتى في الجنازات، أكدت العلاقات
but also transformed
و تحولت أيضا
in a ritual drama that highlights
في طقوس درامية التي تبرز
the most salient feature about death in this place:
الميزة الأكثر بروزا عن الموت في هذا المكان:
its impact on life and the relationships of the living.
تأثيرها على الحياة والعلاقات المعيشية.
So all of this focus on death
لذلك كل هذا التركيز على الموت
doesn't mean that Torajans don't aspire
لا يعني أن التوراجيين لا يطمحون
to the ideal of a long life.
إلى مثل أعلى للحياة طويلة.
They engage in many practices
يخوضون في العديد من الممارسات
thought to confer good health
يعتقد أن تمنح صحة جيدة
and survival to an advanced age.
والبقاء على قيد الحياة لسن متقدمة.
But they don't put much stock
لكنهم لا يضعون الكثير من المال
in efforts to prolong life in the face of debilitating illness
في الجهود الرامية إلى إطالة أمد الحياة في مواجهة المرض الموهن
or in old age.
أو في سن الشيخوخة.
It's said in Toraja that everybody has
ويقال في توراجا أن الجميع لديه
sort of a predetermined amount of life.
نوعا ما كمية محددة سلفا من الحياة.
It's called the sunga'.
تسمى السونجا.
And like a thread, it should be allowed to unspool
و كخيط في لولب الخيوط، ينبغي أن نكون قادرين على فكه
to its natural end.
إلى نهايته الطبيعية.
So by having death as a part
لذلك من خلال وجود الموت كجزء
of the cultural and social fabric of life,
من النسيج الثقافي والاجتماعي للحياة،
people's everyday decisions about their health
القرارات اليومية للناس حول صحتهم
and healthcare are affected.
والرعاية الصحية تتأثر .
The patriarch of my husband's maternal clan,
بطريرك العشيرة الأم لزوجي،
Nenet Katcha,
&amp;quot;نينيت كاتشا&amp;quot;
is now approaching the age of 100, as far as we can tell.
الآن يقترب من سن 100، بقدر ما يمكننا أن نحزر.
And there are increasing signs
وهناك مؤشرات متزايدة
that he is about to depart on his own journey for Puya.
أنه على وشك المغادرة في رحلته الخاصة لبويا.
And his death will be greatly mourned.
و وفاته سيتم نعيها إلى حد كبير.
But I know that my husband's family
لكنني أعرف أن عائلة زوجي
looks forward to the moment
تتطلع إلى اللحظة
when they can ritually display
عندما يمكنهم عقائديا عرض
what his remarkable presence has meant to their lives,
ما يعني لهم وجوده الملحوظ في حياتهم،
when they can ritually recount
عندما يمكنهم إعادة سرد
his life's narrative,
سيرة حياته عقائديا،
weaving his story
نسج قصته
into the history of their community.
في تاريخ مجتمعهم.
His story is their story.
قصته هي قصتهم.
His funeral songs will sing them a song about themselves.
أغاني جنازته سوف تغني لهم أغنية عن أنفسهم.
And it's a story that has no discernible beginning,
وهي قصة لا يوجد لديها بداية ملحوظ،
no foreseeable end.
و لا نهاية منظورة.
It's a story that goes on
إنها قصة تطول
long after his body no longer does.
فترة أطول من أكثر من جسمه .
People ask me if I'm frightened or repulsed
يسألني الناس إذا أنا خائفة أو مشمئزة
by participating in a culture
من خلال المشاركة في ثقافة
where the physical manifestations of death
حيث المظاهر المادية للوفاة
greet us at every turn.
تحيينا في كل مرة.
But I see something profoundly transformative
ولكنني أرى شيئا عميقا متحولا
in experiencing death as a social process
في تجربة الموت كعملية اجتماعية
and not just a biological one.
و ليست مجرد عملية بيولوجية.
In reality, the relationship between the living and the dead
في الواقع، العلاقة بين الأحياء والأموات
has its own drama in the U.S. healthcare system,
لديها الدراما الخاصة بها في نظام الرعاية الصحية الامريكي،
where decisions about how long to stretch
حيث القرارات حول كيف إطالة تمدد
the thread of life are made based on our emotional
خيط الحياة مصنوعة إستنادا إلى
and social ties with the people around us,
الروابط العاطفية و الإجتماعية مع الناس من حولنا،
not just on medicine's ability to prolong life.
ليس فقط على قدرة الطب على إطالة أمد الحياة.
We, like the Torajans,
نحن، كالتوراجيين،
base our decisions about life
نؤسس قراراتنا عن الحياة
on the meanings and the definitions
على المعاني والتعاريف
that we ascribe to death.
التي ننسبها إلى الموت.
So I'm not suggesting that anyone in this audience
لذلك أنا لا أقترح أن أي شخص في هذا الجمهور
should run out and adopt the traditions
يجب أن يمضي و يتبنى تقاليد
of the Torajans.
التوراجيين.
It might be a little bit difficult
قد يكون من الصعب قليلا
to put into play in the United States.
لتجريبها في الولايات المتحدة.
But I want to ask what we can gain
ولكن أريد أن أسأل ما يمكننا كسب
from seeing physical death not only as a biological process
من رؤية الموت الجسدي ليس فقط بإعتباره عملية بيولوجية
but as part of the greater human story.
ولكن كجزء من قصة الإنسان الكبرى.
What would it be like to look on
ما من شأنه أن يكون مثل النظر في
the expired human form with love
شكل الإنسان المنتهي الصلاحية بحب
because it's so intimately a part of who we all are?
لأنه بشكل وثيق جدا جزء منا نحن جميعا؟
If we could expand our definition of death
إذا ما تمكنا من توسيع تعريفنا للوفاة
to encompass life,
ليشمل الحياة،
we could experience death as part of life
يمكننا أن نواجه الموت كجزء من الحياة
and perhaps face death
وربما نواجه الموت
with something other than fear.
بشيء آخر غير الخوف.
Perhaps one of the answers to the challenges
ربما يكون واحدا من الأجوبة على التحديات
that are facing the U.S. healthcare system,
التي تواجه نظام الرعاية الصحية الإمريكي،
particularly in the end-of-life care,
ولا سيما في رعاية نهاية الحياة،
is as simple as a shift in perspective,
هو بسيط مثل التحول في المنظور،
and the shift in perspective in this case
والتحول في المنظور في هذه الحالة
would be to look at the social life of every death.
سيكون لإلقاء نظرة على الحياة الاجتماعية لكل حالة وفاة.
It might help us recognize that the way we limit
قد تساعدنا على إدراك أن الطريقة التي تحد من
our conversation about death
حديثنا عن الموت
to something that's medical or biological
لشيء يكون طبيا أو بيولوجيا
is reflective of a larger culture that we all share
هو إنعكاس لثقافة أكبر نشتركها جميعا
of avoiding death, being afraid of talking about it.
تجنب الموت، والخوف من الحديث حول هذا الموضوع.
If we could entertain and value
لو إستطعنا ترفيه وتقييم
other kinds of knowledge about life,
أنواع أخرى من المعرفة عن الحياة،
including other definitions of death,
بما في ذلك التعاريف الأخرى للموت،
it has the potential to change the discussions
فلديها القدرة على تغيير المناقشات
that we have about the end of life.
التي لدينا عن نهاية الحياة.
It could change the way that we die,
يمكن أن تغير الطريقة التي نموت بها،
but more importantly,
ولكن الأهم من ذلك،
it could transform the way that we live.
يمكن أن تغير الطريقة التي نعيش فيها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)